<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Domus ordinata A funerall sermon, preached in the citie of Bristoll, the fiue and twentith day of Iune, 1618. at the buriall of his kinswoman, Mistresse Needes, wife to Mr. Arthur Needes, and sister to Mr. Robert Rogers of Bristoll. By Iohn Warren, minister of Gods word at Much-Clacton in Essex.</title>
            <author>Warren, John, Vicar of Great Clacton.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1618</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14794</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25094</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100741</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836570</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836570</idno>
            <idno type="VID">851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14794)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1191:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Domus ordinata A funerall sermon, preached in the citie of Bristoll, the fiue and twentith day of Iune, 1618. at the buriall of his kinswoman, Mistresse Needes, wife to Mr. Arthur Needes, and sister to Mr. Robert Rogers of Bristoll. By Iohn Warren, minister of Gods word at Much-Clacton in Essex.</title>
                  <author>Warren, John, Vicar of Great Clacton.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 34 [i.e. 35], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, and are to be solde by Iohn Harison, dwelling in Pater-noster-row, at the signe of the Vnicorne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1618.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 35 misnumbered 34.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A funerall sermon.</note>
                  <note>The second leaf is either unsigned or signed "[par.]2".</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 25094a on UMI microfilm reel 1191.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Needes, --  Mrs. --  (Arthur), d. 1618.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Domus ordinata.</p>
            <p>A FVNERALL SERMON, Preached in the Citie of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> the fiue and twentith day of Iune, 1618. <hi>at the buriall of his kinſwoman, Miſtreſſe</hi> Needes, <hi>wife to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Arthur Needes, <hi>and</hi> ſiſter to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robert Rogers of</hi> Briſtoll.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iohn Warren,</hi> Miniſter of Gods word at <hi>Much-Clacton</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <q>IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Nicholas Okes</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> and are to be ſolde by <hi>Iohn Hariſon,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Pater-noſter-row,</hi> at the ſigne of the <hi>Vnicorne.</hi> 1618.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:851:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, my very good Lord, <hi>Richard, Lord Dacres</hi> of the <hi>South:</hi> grace and peace.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, That which vnwilling I was to offer vnto the view of the world, vntill it was wreſted from mee, by the earneſt deſires of my good friends, am I now willing to ſend forth as a remembrance of my dutifull affection to you. Thus I ſatisfie their deſires in publiſhing this Sermon: and mine owne, in dedicating the ſame vnto your Lordſhip. For howſoeuer diſtance of place is large betweene vs, yet neither is my affection to your Lordſhip, ſo long ſince begun, now diminiſhed: neither
<pb facs="tcp:851:3"/>haue I found your Lordſhip vnmindefull of mee, whom you haue proſecuted with good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours. It may be I ſhall bee condemned for ſending to one in the prime of his age, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of death. But this well peruſed will make you die not the ſooner, but the happier. Olde age is already come to death: this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon teacheth how to meete with death before it commeth. The ſame ſpirit of God which ſaide,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note> Remember thy Creator in the daies of thy youth: <hi>doth knowe that it is fit in young yeares alſo to remember our end.</hi> Oh that they were wiſe,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.29</note> then they would vnderſtand this, they would conſider their latter end: <hi>was the wiſh of God for the</hi> Iſraelites. <hi>It is the way to bee wiſe,</hi> to number our dayes.
<note place="margin">Pſalm. 90.12</note> 
               <hi>Amongſt the Nobles of Egypt whiles they banquited, was carried the picture of death, and theſe wordes ſpoken:</hi> Looke vpon this,
<note place="margin">Herodot. in Enterpe.</note> and ſo eate and reioyce, as that you remember your ſelfe ſhall once be ſuch. <hi>The traine of birdes guideth their flight: and the remembrance of our ends may direct our life. Euen in yong yeares then, let this booke be as</hi> Philip <hi>of</hi> Macedon
<pb facs="tcp:851:3"/>
               <hi>his boy, ſaying,</hi> Memento Philippe, quod homo es, <hi>Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, you are mortall. And my earneſt prayer is, that as it may be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as a token of my dutifull reſpect to your Lordſhip, and to your honourable Lady, ſo it may bee ſome little furtherance, that you both may ſtill and ſtill liue honourably, and in a good age die Chriſtianly: All which your good beginnings doe largely promiſe.</hi> Much-Clacton. Iuly <hi>the</hi> 26. 1618.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips in all duty to be commanded, <hi>Iohn Warren.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:851:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:851:4"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not for any exellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, which I eſteeeme to be in this my worke, that I thus publiſhit. Such hath beene the reſpect which I haue alwayes borne vnto my louing and kinde Vncle M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Mathew Warren,</hi> at this time one of the Sheriffes of <hi>Briſtoll:</hi> and ſuch haue the curteſies beene which I found at his hands, at the hands of my coſen M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Robert Rogers,</hi> brother to this diſceaſed Gentlewoman, at the hands of both their wiues, and alſo of many ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens in that famous Citie: that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not to ſatisfie them in divulging this, which by no ſmall number of them, with more then ordinary importunity hath beene requeſted. They earneſtly proteſted to haue receiued much fruit
<pb facs="tcp:851:5"/>at the hearing. That it may now bring forth fruit in thee (Reader,) let it bee in thy hands, as a <hi>Deaths head,</hi> to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thy end: take it as the clock ſtriketh, as thou thinkeſt vpon thy worldly ſtore, and as thou remembreſt thy conſcience; apply it line by line: and then as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſtood triumphing with the head of dead <hi>Goliah</hi> in his hand: ſo when the time of thy diſſolution commeth, (although others at the like time, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſeleſſe, or elſe yell &amp; houle; thou ſhalt dye as ioyfully, as if death had no venome; crying out triumphantly in the midſt of the pangs of death,
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15</note> 
               <hi>O death where is thy ſting?</hi> When the ſeruants in the citie of <hi>Tyre,</hi> had ſlaine their Lords and Maſters, they agreed to chuſe him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them to bee king, who ſhould firſt eſpy the Sunne riſing the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iuſtin. lib.</hi> 18.</note> when they were all aſſembled to this purpoſe, whiles all the reſt ſtood with their faces looking into the Eaſt, onely <hi>Strato</hi> looked vpon the high mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines weſtward: for doing whereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:851:5"/>hee were at the firſt derided, yet when by this means he firſt deſtroied the reflection of the Sun-beames, then was this face of his iudged, not to be <hi>Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ingenij ratio,</hi> from a ſpeculation of a ſeruile braine, but of ſome more noble ſpirit.
<note place="margin">Malac. 4.</note> So whiles ſome looke for <hi>Chriſt the Sunne of righteouſneſſe,</hi> in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſome in the markets, ſome in other places, if you looke religiouſly to the Sun-ſetting of your life, towardes your death, it may be a meanes for you with great ioy, firſt, to diſcerne the Sunne of righteouſneſſe fauourably ſhining vpon you. Theſe things, if thou haſt any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance to obtaine by this ſamll work; thou wilt firſt thanke God for his gifts, next thoſe citizens of <hi>Briſtoll,</hi> who were the meanes that it came to thy view: and laſtly, thou wilt pray for mee, that the dew of heauen may deſcend vpon my labours to thy further good, and in this hope I commend thee to God, and this ſmall worke to thy good vſage.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt:</hi> Iohn Warren.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:851:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:851:6"/>
            <head>The Preface before the reading of the Text.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the name of the iuſt might be had in remembrance, it is the laudable cuſtome of our Church, at funerall meetings to recite the vertues of the deceaſed, as the <hi>widdowes ſhewed the coats and garments which Dorcas made whiles ſhe was with them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 9.89.</note> yet are there two things which will make mee very ſparing at this time, in the performance of this duty: firſt, leaſt our conſanguinity, and neareneſſe in blood and kinred ſhould make any thinke I ſpeake more out of partiality, then out of iudgement. Secondly, becauſe how neere ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I was vnto her in blood, yet in reſpect of conuerſation, I was a ſtranger. Yet thus much may I truely ſay, that ſhe is generally reported to haue beene towards her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb facs="tcp:851:7"/>full of curteſie, towards her husband full of ſuch loue as himſelfe witneſſed to me, that although they liued together many years, ſhee neuer ſought for any thing towards him, but loue and peace towardes God, religious: inſomuch, that I viſiting her but the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her death, when ſhe could ſcarſely ſpeak to man, ſhe was very deſirous to ſpeake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God by prayer: and comforted herſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I know that he who was the God of Daniel, is my God:</hi> not doubting but the ſame God will deliuer her from all paines and ſorrowes: which we all with ioy remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, leaue her in the hands of God, and that we may thither alſo come at the laſt, let vs heare what the ſpirit ſaith for vs.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:851:7"/>
            <head>A FVNERALL SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESA. 38.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Put thy houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not liue.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Icknes (a Sergeant belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Mayrolty of death,) had ſeazed vpon the body of King <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah,</hi> to vrge him to pay Nature her debt. And whiles hee was vnder this arreſt, the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> was ſent vnto him from God, to preach that in his eares, that ſicknes preached in euery part of his bodie, to wit, that hee ſhould now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently die: and withall to giue him this admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition to prepare himſelfe for death, <hi>Put thy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:851:8"/>houſe in order, for thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which wordes there are theſe two parts to be obſerued: firſt, an exhortation, <hi>Put thy houſe in order:</hi> ſecondly, a commination or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing, <hi>for thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the force of the exhortation dependeth vpon the commination, and as the manners of men are now a dayes, few prepare themſelues for death, vntill they beginne to haue ſome fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of it: therefore in the handling of theſe parts, the firſt ſhall be laſt, and the laſt ſhall be firſt, and I will firſt ſpeake of the commination, and ſecondly of the exhortation.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>Thou ſhalt die, and not liue.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Breui moriturus es, &amp; non viues,</hi> ſaith <hi>Treme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> Thou ſhalt ſpeedily die, and not liue long; not denying but hee ſhould liue in the next worlde, but doubling the ſence in variety of words, to expreſſe the certainty of his meſſage, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſpeedily die, and not liue heere any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this commination, I obſerue three things for our admonition, firſt, ſomething common to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> with vs; ſecondly, there are here ſomethings peculiar to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> not common to vs; thirdly, wee muſt conſider the euent of this prediction.</p>
               <p>Firſt,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> here is one thing in this commination or prediction, which is common to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and to all fleſh, and is therefore called the <hi>way of all fleſh</hi> or of <hi>all the world. Ioſhu.</hi> 23.14. that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:851:8"/>is, death. <hi>For what man liueth, and ſhall not ſee death? Pſal.</hi> 89.48. <hi>ſtatutum eſt hominibus, &amp;c. It is appointed to men, that they ſhall once die: Heb.</hi> 9.27. there is a ſtatute lawe enacted in heauen for it, which cannot be diſanulled. We reade in the fift of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> of many men that liued many hundreds of yeares, yet none of them but dyed at the laſt. At the command of <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> the Sunne ſtood ſtill for a while in <hi>Gibea</hi> and the Moone in the valley of <hi>Aialon,</hi> yet not for euer, but they found their going downe: ſo may ſome mans life ſtand for a while, longer then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but yet at the laſt death catcheth them. To Princes and Magiſtrates God ſpeaketh, <hi>I ſayde yee are Gods, but yee ſhall die like men: Pſal.</hi> 82. The life of man being preſerued by a <hi>calidum humidum,</hi> neuer yet could the ſearchers of nature finde meanes to preſerue it alwayes. When any malefactor is condemned to death and ſpeedy execution, the Magiſtrate may par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him, and giue him his life to warrant him againſt the executioner, but not againſt death: yea when death commeth to the Magiſtrate himſelfe, hee cannot repriue himſelfe, dye hee muſt. Glaſſe is brittle and cannot laſt long, it is ſubiect to ſo many knockes: yet if it be ſet in ſome ſafe place from knockes, it may endure many ages. It is not ſo with man, who though hee eſcape all outward violence, yet is borne with ſinne and conſequently with corruption to breed his death, one <hi>Henoch,</hi> one <hi>Helias,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:851:9"/>might bee tranſlated, that they ſhould not ſee death, ſo to confirme our hope of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection by the mighty power of God: but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any more. <hi>Death is gone ouer all men. Rom.</hi> 5. I neede not longer to amplifie this point: yee are not now as <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> once were, whiles they neuer ſawe a man to die; euery Church-yard, euery age, euery ſickneſſe, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth this mortallity: and yee will alſo ſay this thing wee all acknowledge. But yet I wiſh wee did ſo acknowledge it, as that wee would lay it to our hearts. We ſcarcely liue as if we ſhould die, no not when we follow others to the graue. In a good paſture where many fat oxen are, the Butcher entreth and fetcheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way one and killeth it: next day he fetcheth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and ſtill thoſe which hee leaueth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, feede and fat themſelues vntill they are fetched to the ſlaughter: not conſidering either what is become of their fellowes, or ſhall bee of themſelues. So when death commeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a multitude of vs, heere taking one, and there another, being preſently ready to fetch vs wee pamper vp our ſelues without ceaſing till death take vs. Did wee conſider our owne endes, wee would alter this courſe, the hand writing vpon the wall made <hi>Baltaſar</hi> tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in euery ioynt, <hi>Daniel</hi> the fift. Oh let the hand-writing of God whereby the number of our daies is determined make vs ſo to liue, as that wee remember wee ſhall not alwaies liue
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:851:9"/>here, for this ſentence is paſſed on vs, <hi>yee ſhall die, and not liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> obſerue in theſe wordes to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> that there are three things peculier to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah:</hi> whereof wee are deſtitute. 1. That herein he was foretold of the time of his death, for ſo the words import: <hi>thou ſhalt preſently die.</hi> But to you I can ſay, you ſhall die, but when I cannot ſay, no not when Phyſitions haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you ouer vnto death. <hi>Man knoweth not his time, Eccleſ.</hi> 9. wee know the Sunne ſhall ſet in the euening, and we perceiue how, &amp; when: wee can ſay, now the Sunne is foure houres high, or two houres, or one houre high: wee cannot ſay ſo of our life: but when wee thinke it is many houres, it may preſently ceaſe; when wee thinke the Sunne of our life is ready to ſet, it may haue farre to runne. To him that drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of many yeares, it was ſaide, <hi>Thou foole, this night ſhall they fetch away thy ſoule, Luk.</hi> 12. <hi>It is not for you to knowe the times and ſeaſons, which the Father hath kept in his owne power</hi> (ſaid our Sauiour to his Diſciples, in the firſt of the <hi>Acts.</hi>) It is not for you; and for our good: If hee that hath now liued threeſcore yeares, ſhould from his infancy bee aſſured that hee ſhould haue liued ſo long, Oh how ſecure would hee haue beene in his ſinnes, whom yet this vncertainty of the time of his death could not awake? <hi>Vtiliter voluit Deus latere illum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, vt ſemper paratum ſit cer, ad expectandum
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:851:10"/>quod eſſe venturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit et quando venturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit neſcit,</hi> ſaid S. <hi>Auſten</hi> of the day of iudgement. So I, of the day of death: It was for our profit, that God would not haue vs to know that day, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that euery day we ſhould prepare for that which may come vpon vs any day, and we are ſure ſhall come vpon vs one day, which wee know not. Oh be carefull this day, which may be thy laſt, thrice happy is that ſeruant, whom his Maſter when hee commeth ſhall finde well doing. <hi>Let your loynes be girded about, and your ſelues like vnto men that waite for their Maſter, when hee ſhall returne from the wedding, Luk.</hi> 12.35. All wee can ſay vnto you is, your Maſter will come, but when, we know not. When ye ſhall die, whether to day, or to morrow, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this moneth or next, whether this yeare or next, we cannot tell; but this wee are ſure of, <hi>die ye ſhall, and not liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In theſe wordes it was foretolde to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> in what place he ſhould die: for, ſo much they intend, thou ſhalt preſently in this place, without time to change often thy place, in this place thou ſhalt die. As for vs, we know where wee were borne, but in what place we ſhall die, vntill wee die wee knowe not: whether in the ſhop, or in the chamber, or in the field, or in the Church, or in a iourney; no place ſo good, as death will not enter, none ſo vile a place, as will diſdaine. <hi>Moſes</hi> had appointed ſome cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of refuge, and we haue had ſanctuaries and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:851:10"/>priuiledged places for men oppreſſed: were there any place in this world a ſanctuary where death might not enter, I doubt not but it wold bee thronged vnto: but there is no place freed here fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death, <hi>pallida mors aequo pulſat pede pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tabernas, regumque turres,</hi> countrie cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Kings courts feel death alike. The Sun is introduced in the Poets ſpeaking thus of it ſelfe, <hi>Omnia qui video, per quem videt omnia mundus:</hi> I ſee all places and things, and by me are all things and places ſeene, the Wiſeman ſaith, <hi>The ſun that ſhineth looketh vpon all things, Eccleaſticus</hi> 42.16. yet are there ſome places from whence the light of the ſun may bee kept; ſo is there not any place from whence death may bee kept. looke for it in euery place: <hi>In omni loco te mors expectat, tu illam omni loco ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecta:</hi> it may be, it runneth by thy horſe ſide as thou rideſt, to take thee downe, it may bee it walketh into the fields, to make thee for euer ſeeing thy home againe. In any caſe take heed of going into any places of ſin and wickednes; it may bee death ſtandeth there, euen there to take thee to thy eternall ſhame. For as for the place of thy death we cannot tell thee: all I can ſay, is onely this, <hi>thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Herein is another thing wherein we dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> he is foretolde the diſeaſe he ſhall die of: for ſo the wordes importe, thou ſhalt not recouer of this ſickneſſe: as for vs we know not the diſeaſe ſhall worke our death, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:851:11"/>our end: no not when wee are ſubiect to ſome grieuous diſeaſe, for ſome other meanes may preuent it. <hi>Vnus naſcendi modus, moriendi mille;</hi> there is but one way for vs all to be born into the world, but a thouſand ſeuerall waies to die, as a broken ſhippe receiueth in water at a thouſand places, ſo wee leake, and take in death in euery part of our body. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> had ſeauen diuels, one man had one, and another had a legion: one man hath one diſeaſe, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſeauen, another hath a whole legion of diſeaſes to bring him to his ende. <hi>Him that eſcapeth from the ſword of Hazael, ſhall Iehuſlay, and him that eſcapeth from the ſword of Iehu, ſhal Eliſhah ſlay,</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 19. ſo him that eſcapeth one meanes of death, another will ſlay. <hi>Pharaoh</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapeth the fire, and periſheth in the Sea, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> is free from the Sea, and is conſumed with fire, <hi>Corah</hi> auoideth the fire, and the earth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth him, <hi>Herod</hi> is free from all theſe, and the wormes eate him, <hi>Ioh</hi> his children eſchew all theſe, and die by the fall of a houſe, the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> ſtand, and they periſh with famine, the <hi>Shunamites</hi> childe is free from theſe, and hee cryeth out, <hi>Oh my head, my head, Antiochus</hi> his head is well, and hee complay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, <hi>Oh my bowels, my bowels, Aſa</hi> his bowels are well, and he exclaimeth, <hi>Oh my feet, my feet;</hi> and what euery one of vs ſhall complaine of, at our laſt and ſoreſt ſickneſſe, it is to vs vacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Onely thrice happy is that perſon, who
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:851:11"/>though he be vncertaine with what diſeaſe his body ſhall bee diſtempered, at the time of his death, ſhal ſo look to himſelf, as that he may be aſſured that his ſoule ſhall not wauer, nor bee diſtuned from God. Thus are we vnlike to <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah,</hi> in this prediction, <hi>Thou ſhalt die and not liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may bee ſome man here may obiect, that many of the heathen men haue beeneforewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the time of their death, as alſo of the place: as was <hi>Alexander</hi> of <hi>Macedonia,</hi> tolde that <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould be fatall to him.
<note place="margin">Quintus Cart.</note> It may be ſome will obiect what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>I knowe yee ſhall ſee my face no more, Act.</hi> 20.25. It may be they will likewiſe obiect what was tolde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Saul</hi> at the houſe of the witch at <hi>Endor,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.19. And from theſe things ſome will thinke, that either by the ſtarres, or ſome other naturall courſes, a man may knowe both the time and place of his death long before. But firſt, as for heathen men, who can denie but God by extrtordinary meanes reuealed further things to them, as to <hi>Pharoah,</hi> and <hi>Nabuchado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſor,</hi> in their dreames, and might by ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary meanes let ſome of them knowe theſe thigns we ſpeake of. Secondly, to thinke that ſuch particular things may bee knowne by the ſtarres, is a meere vanity, for though I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not but that they may haue ſome power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſenſuall inclination, yet neither ſo much as that man is ſubiect thereto vpon neceſſity,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:851:12"/>according to the old ſaying in the Schooles, <hi>Aſtra inclinant,
<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Andre. epiſt. Cic eſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. ad M. W. librum. reſponſ. pa.</hi> 108.</note> non neceſsitant:</hi> neither yet in caſuall actions, ſo farre as to direct particular iournies, whereon theſe things depend, as Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſheweth by his inſtance,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de ciuit. Dei. li.</hi> 5 <hi>ca.</hi> 2 <hi>Tacit. Annal. li.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 5.</note> which for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uities ſake I doe but name: and as for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous prediction of <hi>Traſullus</hi> vnto <hi>Tiberius,</hi> (which is ſo much admired by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> as alſo by <hi>Xiphiline:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Xiphilin. li.</hi> 54. <hi>in Aug. Caeſar. Lipſ. monit &amp; exempl. polit. li.</hi> 1. <hi>ca.</hi> 5 <hi>Baſil. in hexem. homil.</hi> 1.</note>) <hi>Lipſius</hi> hath well obſerued that it might well be done, not by Aſtronomy, but by chance. So might it be to <hi>Alexander,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the place of their death by chance is thus foretolde: for if any man ſhall thinke to vſe the ſtarres to ſuch end, I muſt for this time briefly bonclude with <hi>Baſil, Aſtrologia iudicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, negotioſiſsima vanitas,</hi> This iudicious Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, is a moſt buſie vanity. As for that of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> it was extraordinary, as was his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reuelations. But for <hi>Saul</hi> his doings by the witch at <hi>Endor,</hi> I ſay no more at this time, but that if it were not an impoſture and ſpoken by chance, yet ſurely it was then extraordinary. So, that ſtill by any naturall meanes we are not aſſured vntill our death, either of the time, place, or meanes of our death, only this we are ſure of, <hi>we ſhall die, and not liue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as wee haue propounded,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> wee muſt come to the third point obſeruable, before wee leaue theſe wordes: and that is the euent of this prediction. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> is here tolde from God, when, where, and how he ſhall die: doth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:851:12"/>it ſo come to paſſe? dyeth hee preſently of this ſickneſſe, and in this place? wee finde it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. For in the third verſe of this chapter, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vpon this meſſage, <hi>Hezekiah turned his face vnto the wall, and prayed vnto the Lord,</hi> and the Lord anſwereth in the fift verſe, <hi>I haue heard thy prayer, and ſeene thy teares, behold I will adde to thy dayes fifteene yeares.</hi> How will he adde to his dayes? <hi>The dayes of man are determined, thou haſt appointed him bounds which hee cannot paſſe, Iob.</hi> 14. Shall <hi>Hezekiah</hi> then liue fifteene yeares longer then God had determined? God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid: but God will adde to the time paſt of his life fifteene yeares, yet to come.</p>
               <p>It may be, that the time paſt of his life, was the longeſt time that hee could haue liued ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of nature. A candle bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo long as the tallow thereof doth endure, when the tallow is conſumed then it goeth out: yet if to the laſt wicke of the candle you put a little oyle, it will burne a little longer then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would: So the life of man endureth as long as that <hi>calidum humidum,</hi> or moyſt heat, is duly preſerued in the body of man; but when that moyſt heate, or hot moyſture is corrupted wholly, then is the life of man naturally extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, as it may be, it was in <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> then God addeth <hi>olem potentiae,</hi> the oyle of his power to prolonge his life, fifteene yeares beyond the naturall period of his time.</p>
               <p>But yet this queſtion remayneth vnſatisfied
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:851:13"/>concerning the euent of this prediction. God foretolde to <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that hee ſhould ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly die in this place, of this diſeaſe. <hi>Hezekiah</hi> now hath his life prolonged for fifteene yeares. How is God true then in the prediction? or how doth God alter his determinations? For the anſwering whereof: true it is which God himſelfe doth ſay, <hi>I am God, and I am not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, Malak.</hi> 3.6. <hi>For hee is not as man that hee ſhould repent,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.29. But briefly to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this perplexed queſtion, <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, hath an excellent ſpeech, <hi>Nouit Deus mutare ſententiam, ſed nunquam nouit mutare decretum,</hi> God knoweth how to change his ſentence, but not his decree. The decree of God was that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah</hi> by praying ſhould obtaine the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his life, for fifteene yeares. To make <hi>Hezekiah</hi> fall to his prayers, God ſendeth the Prophet with this menacing meſſage; yet as in all menaces of God, is there a ſecret excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: vnleſſe <hi>Hezekiah</hi> earneſtly pray. So that there was an exception to be vnderſtood, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not expreſſed. Yee may ſee the dealing of God with King <hi>Abimelech:</hi> God threatened him becauſe hee had taken from <hi>Abraham</hi> his wife: <hi>Beholde, thou art but dead, Gen.</hi> 20. Ye ſee the ſentence in ſhew is reſolute: yet was there a ſecret condition to bee vnderſtood, for you ſhall finde it expreſſed in the ſeauenth verſe of the ſame chapter thus, <hi>If thou deliuer her not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, thou ſhalt die the death.</hi> Thus muſt we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:851:13"/>the meſſage ſent to <hi>Niniueh, yet forty dayes, and Niniueh ſhall be deſtroyed, Iona.</hi> 3. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, ſinfull <hi>Niniueh</hi> ſhall bee deſtroyed: <hi>Niniueh</hi> ſhalbe deſtroied if it do not repent, but the ſins of <hi>Niniueh,</hi> ſhal be forgiuen if it doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. So although God himſelf in thine own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tell thee, that for thy horrible ſins, thou ſhalt be eternally tormented: yet if thou ſhalt ſeriouſly repent, God for Chriſt his ſake will change his ſentence, that ſo hee may bring to paſſe his decree of ſauing thee. And thus much ſhall ſuffice to haue ſpoken of the firſt part of my text, I come now to the ſecond, the exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Put thy houſe in order.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Seeing God hath ſent to <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of death,
<note place="margin">1. There muſt be a preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for death.</note> hee ſendeth alſo vnto him the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice to prepare himſelfe for death. An admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition neceſſary for vs all. <hi>Plerique inter mortis metum, &amp; vitae tormenta miſeri fluctuant; vt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere nolint, &amp; mori neſciunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca;</hi> Many miſerable men wauer betweene the ſorrowes of life, and the feare of death: to liue they are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing, yet how to die they know not. We vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake no very long iourney, without long preparation of things neceſſary: death is our longeſt iourney, and in that voyage the ſoule will neede much preparation a forehand. No great and dangerous warre is vndertaken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great and long preparation of armes and vittailes. In death there is a ſorer conflict. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:851:14"/>lamenting <hi>Abner,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Died Abner as a foole dieth?</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.33. And many notable men die as fooles, becauſe they prepare not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for death. You may not come to receiue Chriſt in the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords ſupper, without good preparation: and can ye thinke that yee ſhall be admitted to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the glory of Ieſus Chriſt, to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Angels, to the innumerable ſocietie of the bleſſed Saints, without due preparing of your ſelues againſt the time of death, the time of your entrance?</p>
               <p n="2">2. There muſt be then a preparation againſt death: but how? ſurely, <hi>Order</hi> is the beſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration. In the generall <hi>Chaos</hi> of all things, there was confuſion: But to bring all things to perfection, God tooke order for <hi>Order,</hi> and of all things ſince, <hi>Ordinatione tua perſeuerant, They continue euen to this day by thy ordinances,</hi> ſayde <hi>Dauid</hi> to God, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.91. The Church of God, is <hi>acies ordinata, as an army with banners, Cant.</hi> 6.9. In the Church of God, it is Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his rule, <hi>Let all things be done honeſtly, and in order,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40. (which that it may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, hee ſaith) <hi>other things will I ſet in order when I come,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.34. For, <hi>Order</hi> conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth all things, confuſion is but diſorder. To prepare a man therefore againſt death, he muſt ſet all things in order: as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſet all things carefully in order, when hee was to meete his brother <hi>Eſau, Gen.</hi> 32. And though <hi>Iob</hi> ſay,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:851:14"/>that in <hi>the ſhadow of death, is no order, Iob.</hi> 10.22. yet if before death, all things be ſet in order, all will bee comfortable; therefore to preuent the miſeries of death ſaith <hi>Eſay,</hi> to <hi>Hezekiah, Put thy houſe in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Not a corner of thy fielde, or a part of thy houſe, but <hi>put thy houſe in order. I and my houſe will ſerue the Lord,</hi> ſaide <hi>Ioſhua, Ioſhu.</hi> 24.15. That thou mayſt bee in order, <hi>Put thy houſe in order.</hi> But what houſe? or how to bee put in order? Men in their dwelling houſes furniſh ſome chiefe roomes, and the other roomes will need the leſſe decking. There be three eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all roomes in this houſe of man, which being put in order, the whole houſe of mans life will be the better ordered. 1. The clock-houſe. 2. The ſtore-houſe. 3. The cloſſet-houſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the clock-houſe, whereby the time of man is ordered: for if the time bee not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but that the clock giue an vncertain ſound, how then ſhall buſineſſe be diſpoſed? this made the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> thus to petition vnto God, <hi>Teach vs, O Lord, ſo to number our dayes, as that wee may apply our hearts vnto wiſedome, Pſal.</hi> 90.12. This numbring of our dayes, is the well orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the clock-houſe: and that they may be well numbred, wee muſt take heede of multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that wee bee not like vnto that rich man, <hi>Luke.</hi> 12. who dreamed of many yeares, when hee had not one night to liue. We muſt rather number them by ſubſtraction firſt, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:851:15"/>then by diuiſion. Firſt, by ſubſtraction ſet downe all the time ye haue liued, ſuppoſe thou art forty or fifty yeares olde, out of thoſe years firſt ſubſtarct the time ſpent in ſleeping, &amp; out of forty yeares, ten will be the leaſt that can be taken; <hi>Humanae vitae publicanus ſomnus,</hi> ſleepe taketh a large tole out of the life of man: then ſubſtract the time ſpent in idleneſſe, <hi>Magna pars vitae nobis perit dum nihil agimus,</hi> ſayde <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca,</hi> out of the other thirty yeares will bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted a very great portion: thirdly, ſubſtract the time ſpent in things vnprofitable, which might as well haue beene left vndone as done, and this alone will cut off the very greateſt part of many mens liues: for <hi>multó maxima pars vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae dum invtilia agimus:</hi> farre greateſt part of life periſheth, while we doe thoſe things which are vnprofitable. And laſt of all, deduct the time ſpent in ſinfull actions, remembring that <hi>The iuſt man falleth ſenen times a day, Pro.</hi> 24.16. let all theſe bee deducted, and then if yee will iudge what remayneth of all the time of our life to prayer, and meditation, and other holy excerciſes, yee ſhall finde a poore pittance in moſt of vs.</p>
               <p>Then number wee our dayes againe by diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and that in ſuch order, as Merchants de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide their debts, ſome deſperate, ſome doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſome few perhaps certaine: your dayes are your debts, for which God will call you to account. The dayes paſt, not well ſpent, are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:851:15"/>deſperate debts, the future dayes are altogether vncertaine: and therefore the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> maketh but a ſuppoſe of it, <hi>Snppoſe a man liue foureſcore yeares, &amp;c. Pſalm.</hi> 90. The preſent time is onely certaine, and to be relied vpon. <hi>Maximum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedimentum boni eſt, quod dependit a craſtino,</hi> the greateſt impediment of being good, is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of it vntill to morrow; the heathen man would haue vs thinke, euery day to bee our laſt day: the Scripture willeth vs to pray but for <hi>panem quotidianum,</hi> our daily bread, and wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs, <hi>to day if wee will heare his voyce, Heb.</hi> 3.7. <hi>beholde now is the acceptable time, beholde now is the day of ſaluation.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. Many poore ſoules now lye in endleſſe torments, which made not good vſe of the preſent time, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their amendement for a time, of which they were diſappointed by death. Thus theu if wee number our dayes firſt by ſubſtraction, ſecondly, by diuiſion: we put our clock-houſe or the houſe of our time in order.</p>
               <p>The next houſe to bee put in order, is the ſtore-houſe, or the houſe of our wealth and worldly eſtate: this no dying man carrieth with him out of this world. <hi>Naked came I out of my mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe,</hi> ſaide <hi>Iob,</hi> in the ſecond chapter of <hi>Iob. Peter</hi> tooke a fiſh in the Sea with mony in the mouth of it: wee come not out of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe with money in our mouthes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe wee carry our wealth with vs. Wealth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:851:16"/>may accompany vs to the graue, afterwardes it ſerueth for no vſe to vs: and therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare vs for death, this our ſtore-houſe muſt be put in order; that from thence may ariſe no confuſion when wee leaue it. Of dying <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> it is ſaide, <hi>Abraham gaue all his goods to Iſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack; And vnto the ſonnes of the concubines which Abraham had, Abraham gaue gifts, Gen.</hi> 25.5.6. Thus dying <hi>Iacob</hi> diſpoſed of his bleſſings, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. I knowe that <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> wiſhed to bee heire to himſelfe, and to ſee the ending and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of all things with his owne perſon. And I make no queſtion, but many a miſerable earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme grieueth infinitely to leaue his wealth, and that hee cannot ſtill liue alwaies to bee his owne heire. But as trauailers that walke a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney on foot, vſe their ſtaues in their hands while they walke, but when they come home they ſet them behinde the doore, or in ſome corner: ſo is man to vſe the ſtaffe of bread, and of his wealth, during the time hee walketh in this world, and when hee is by death entring into his long home, he is to order it in ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient place, that it may ſtand fit for others, who ſhall neede it. The ſtore-houſe then of our worldly eſtate muſt bee put in order againſt death: For firſt, no man can alwaies keepe it: ſecondly, others ſhall neede it: and thirdly, vnleſſe it bee put in order, diſcord and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enſueth amongſt the liuing.</p>
               <p>But now for the manner how this ſtore-houſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:851:16"/>ſhould be put in order: that hee who maketh his will may obſerue the will of God, that ſo the teſtament of man may agree with the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God, theſe things following muſt bee obſerued. Firſt, that a man leaue not the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous curſe of God vpon his ſtore-houſe, and them to whom hee ſhall leaue it, let a man bee ſure, that if hee haue ill gotten goods, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them again to the owners, or their heires, as <hi>Zacheus</hi> did, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. <hi>If I haue deceiued any man by forged cauillation, I reſtore vnto him foure folde.</hi> This duty, as of all others it is moſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, ſo is there none more neceſſary, vnleſſe a man carry with him an <hi>anathema</hi> from God out of this worlde, and leaue to the reſt of his goods rottenneſſe and corruption. Conſider why God threateneth the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſo ſorely, <hi>The ſpoile of the poore is in your houſes, Eſay.</hi> 3.14 marke what the Prophet <hi>Habakkuk</hi> ſaith, <hi>The ſtone ſhall cry out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber ſhall anſwere it: Woe vnto him that buildeth a towne with blood, and erecteth a cittie with iniquity, Hab.</hi> 2.11.12. obſerue what Saint <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>Behold the hyre of the labourers which haue reaped your fields (which is of you kept backe by fraude) cryeth and the cryes of them which haue reaped, are entred into the eares of the Lord of hoaſts, Iam.</hi> 5.4. What a lamentable caſe is here to be obſerued; thou lyeſt ſicke vpon thy bed, euery houre expecting to bee carryed vnto the tribunall of God: thou through hope and feare
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:851:17"/>cryeſt vnto God for mercy. In the meane time, in euery corner of thy houſe, is one thing or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea perhappes thy very bedde thou lyeſt vpon, gotten by vniuſtice and oppreſſion, all crying vnto God for vengeance againſt thee &amp; thine heire: and that with a lowder note, then thy ſicke heart or voyce is able to reach vnto. Oh remember <hi>Samuel,</hi> how hee would cleare himſelfe with all care, <hi>Whoſe oxe haue I taken? or whoſe aſſe haue I taken?</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12, 13. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaide to the King of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> that hee would not take of his ſo much as a ſhooe latchet, <hi>leaſt thou ſhouldeſt ſay, I haue made Abraham rich, Gen.</hi> 14.23.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to order this ſtore-houſe, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer will bee helped by God in ſickneſſe, and in time of neede, muſt bee open handed to the poore: to ſuch is God a helpe in ſicknes, mark the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Bleſſed is hee that conſidereth the poore and needr, Pſalm.</hi> 41.1. How is hee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? <hi>The Lord ſhall viſite him when hee lyeth ſicke vpon his bed,</hi> in the third verſe of the ſame <hi>Pſal.</hi> When one lyeth ſicke vpon his bed, it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to bee viſited by his friends: yet of ſome may it be ſayd, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſayd to his friends: <hi>Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable comforters are yee, and Phiſitians of no va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, Iob.</hi> 16.2. one commeth and talketh of your olde madde prancks with a madde minde, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commeth, and hee is full of contention with you; a third commeth, and hee is all for the world with you; a fourth commeth, and he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:851:17"/>is all in the paſſion of thoſe to whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>What doe ye weeping and breaking my heart? Act.</hi> 21.13. all miſerable comforters, but when God commeth to viſite thee in thy ſickneſſe: Oh the grace and peace that hee ſhall ſpeake vnto thy ſoule, neuer man ſpake as hee will ſpeake. Put thy ſtore-houſe then in order, ſo as they that are in need, may by thee be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and God will remember thee, and viſite thee in time of neede. The ſpaniell that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſome deepe or large ditch or riuer, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer which hee cannot get vnleſſe hee ſwimme, will vſe the benefit of the water to ſwim ouer; but aſſoone as he hath paſſed to the dry ſhoare, hee will ſhake off the ſuperfluous water, and ſo moyſten the dry ground. You haue a great Sea of this worlde to paſſe ouer, when you come from your mothers wombe, ere you come to your graue: you vſe your wealth as the water, by helpe whereof you may ſwimme ouer, when you are vpon the ſhoare, Oh ſhake off from your aboundance that which may refreſh the weary and needy ſoule: <hi>Make you friends with the riches of iniquity, that when yee ſhall want, they may receiue you into euerlaſting habitations, Luk.</hi> 16.9.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in diſpoſing of the other part of the ſtore-houſe, to giue all to ſtrangers, and not to wife and children, or the neareſt in blood of the ſame familie, ſeemeth to be contrarie to the lawe of nature, and the rule of Saint <hi>Paul, If
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:851:18"/>there bee any that prouideth not for his owne, and namely for them of his houſholde, hee denyeth the faith, and is worſe then an infidell,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. <hi>Abraham gaue all his goods that hee had to Iſaack, to the ſonnes of his concubines hee gaue gifts. Gen.</hi> 25.5.6. In the family, then there is reſpect to bee had, who is to haue more, who leſſe. And by the ſpeech of old <hi>Iacob</hi> to his eldeſt ſon <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ben,</hi> it ſeemeth to be grounded vpon the law of nature, that the eldeſt ſonne ſhould bee moſt regarded: <hi>Ruben, mine eldeſt ſonne, thou art my might, and the beginning of my ſtrength, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of my dignity, and the excellency of my power, Gen.</hi> 49.3. although for ſome eſpeciall cauſes it hath otherwaies come to paſſe, as that <hi>Ephraim</hi> is preferred before <hi>Manaſſes, Gen.</hi> 48. and <hi>the elder ſhall ſerue the younger, Rom.</hi> 9. and as for that <hi>lex ſalica,</hi> whereby women are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barred from inheriting, it ſeemeth contrarie to the courſe which God took for the daughters of <hi>Zelophehad, Num.</hi> 27.7. I will not ſay more but this, that it ſeemeth vnreaſonable to leaue one amongſt many children a coach to ride in, and the other ſcarcely a paire of ſhooes to walke with: one all, and the other none: and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it is to leaue all well without an earneſt praier of the bleſſing of God vpon all. Thus muſt the ſtore-houſe be ſet in order.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And now I come to the cloſſet-houſe, to ſhew how that muſt bee put in order: and by this cloſſet-houſe, I meane the cloſe houſe of a
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:851:18"/>mans ſoule and conſcience: cloſe as yet from the world, but to God onely open and to a mans ſelfe. And indeed although a man put all the reſt in order, if he doe not put this houſe in order; how much better is hee then <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel?</hi> of whom the Scripture ſaith, that hee <hi>put his houſholde in order, and hanged himſelfe,</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.23. for ſuch a man ordereth his wealth, and vtterly ouerthroweth himſelfe. How this more priuate cloſſet-houſe muſt bee ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if wee well conſider, wee finde that as the ſoules internall operations, are either in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or in the more particular working of the affections and of the will; ſo the meanes to put the houſe of the ſoule in order againſt death, are either in meditation, or in action. And firſt in meditation, there muſt bee diuerſe things ordered: by keeping the ſoule in often meditating vpon theſe three things; firſt, to meditate of death: ſecondly, of this life: and thirdly, of the great change which will happen to diuerſe men preſently after death.</p>
               <p>Firſt by meditation of death,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and often thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof before it commeth; I know that to many worldly-minded men, whiles they are in health and wealth, it is euen as death but to thinke of death, <hi>Oh death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that liueth at reſt in his poſſeſsions, Eccleſiaſt.</hi> 41.1. better thoughts for him, hee iudgeth to be the remembrance of his neighbours miſery, his owne worldly feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:851:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>his full bagges, his great ſtore-houſe of coſtly buildings: <hi>Is not this great Babell which I haue built, Daniel.</hi> 4.27. and thus, they ſpend their dayes in wealth, and ſuddenly they goe downe to the graue, <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.13. I know that the Emperour <hi>Otho</hi> did iudge it to bee the part of a cowardly and weake minde, often to ſpeake and thinke of death. But our bleſſed Sauiour (who is farre greater then the greateſt of the ſons of men) did very many times both thinke and ſpeake of his death, to his diſciples: to leaue vs an example, that whoſoeuer will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelfe for death, muſt thinke of it many times in his life. But what ſhould a man thinke of death? That a man may well meditate of death, ſo as he may thereby <hi>put the houſe of his ſoule in order</hi> for death, there are three things to be meditated on.</p>
               <p>Firſt, let a man remember what death is to all men by nature: and there hee ſhall finde that death neuer came into the world but by ſinne:
<note place="margin">By ſinne came death, 1. Cor. 15.21.</note> 
                  <hi>The wages of ſinne is death, Rom.</hi> 6.23. and by that meanes entring with an enemy, it ſelfe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is an enemy to the nature of man: ſo is it called by the Apoſtle, <hi>The laſt enemy that ſhall be deſtroyed, is death.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. Life of it ſelfe is a great bleſſing of God to euery liuing thing: and no liuing creature, but will ſtriue to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the life of it ſelfe, and to ſhunne death: the poore worme, or bird, <hi>tam viuit vitâ quám Angelos,</hi> ſaid Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and is deſirous to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:851:19"/>preſerue its life, as the Angels would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theirs. And that they may doe ſo, God hath giuen to euery liuing creature ſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or luſtre whiles they liue; and ordered things ſo, that few or no liuing creatures dye without pangs; yea euen very hearbes &amp; trees when they die, loſe their luſtre and beauty, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery liuing creature therefore, euen from the higheſt Angell, to the meaneſt plant, either by reaſon, ſence, or naturall inſtinct, ſhunneth death as an enemy. Yet this enemy which when it commeth bringeth pangs, when it is come, ſpoyleth the naturall luſtre in all things, muſt wee meditate to yeeld our ſelues, <hi>Put the houſe of thy ſoule in order, with this meditation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, meditate what death is to euill men; beaſts die, and after the few pangs of death, they feele no more: a wicked man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and when hee is heere dead, yet hee is not all dead: but with an endleſſe lingring death is alwaies dying in endleſſe torments, ſo that he cannot bee altogether dead: the ſoule periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>Non it a, vt non ſit, ſed vt male ſit: &amp; eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialiter viuere, non amittit, ſed beate viuere per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit,</hi> ſaid <hi>Gregory,</hi> in the fourth of his morrals; The ſoule periſheth not ſo that it dyeth, but ſo that it liueth moſt miſerably, if it felt no more after this death, there would bee an ende of paines: but after this bodily death, by reaſon of their paines, men ſhall ſeeke death, and ſhall not finde it, and ſhall deſire to die, and death
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:851:20"/>ſhall flee from them, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 9.6. Here in ſome ſore ſickneſſe, great loſſes, heauy croſſes, men wiſh for death, what are all the troubles of this life, to thoſe after bodily death? wee may well here take vppe the wordes of the heathen man, who ſaide that death was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of all fearfull things the moſt fearefull. How may a guilty man who hath ſpent his dayes in iollitie, at the houre of, his death crye to his trembling ſoule, as the Emperour <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> did, <hi>Animula, vagula, blandula, Hoſpes comeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que corporis, Quo nunc abibis in loco, Pallida, rigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, nudula, Nec vt ſoles, dabis iocos?</hi> Oh my wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, flattering, little ſoule, the gueſt and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion of my body, into what places art thou now to goe, pale, affrighted, naked, neither as thou wert wont ſhalt thou henceforth make me merry? By this meditation of death, <hi>Put thy houſe, thy cloſet-houſe in order,</hi> that thou mayeſt ſhun this euill in death.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, meditate what death is to good men. In the greateſt pangs of death, they feele ioy; after death they loſe not their luſtre, but get a farre greater then euer they had: true it is, that euen of the Saints Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death is an enemie,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.26. But ſuch a one, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now conquered, ſerueth but for the glory of the conquerers: The naturall man ſhunneth death, the ſanctified man although hee ſtay till death come, yet <hi>he deſireth to be diſſolued, Philip.</hi> 1.23. <hi>death is to mee aduantage, Phil.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paris
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:851:20"/>ad laetitiam, mater maeroris, vſurparis ad glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam, gloriae inimica, vſurparis ad introitum reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, porta inferni: Bern. in cant. ſer.</hi> 26. Thou art now vſed to mirth, O mother of ſorrowes: thou ſerueth vs to glory, O enemy of glory, thou helpeſt our paſſage to the kingdome, which wert the gate of hell: it bringeth vs to the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſence of the Trinitie, where all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and bleſſed Saincts, will ioyfully embrace vs, after all our labours ended. Oh let this me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of this happy eſtate after death, ſerue for vs to helpe to <hi>put thy houſe, thy cloſſet-houſe in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will be, and haue beene very briefe in theſe things; the time compelleth mee. Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> let a man meditate what this life is: men are fond of it, <hi>That skinne for skinne, and all that euer a man hath, will he giue for his life: Iob.</hi> 2.4. &amp; therfore it ſhould ſeem to be a moſt matchleſſe thing. God forbid that I ſhould by wordes or thought debaſe ſo glorious a work of the liuing God, as life is. Yet what our life in ſinne hath made life to bee, let mee ſpeake a little. Firſt, when wee conſider ſome in their wealth, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, honour and ſtrength, it appeareth I muſt needes ſay, a beautifull life: but yet euen as it is then, it is but as that <hi>mare vitreum, the Sea of Gods Glaſſe, Reuel.</hi> 4.6. a Sea full of ſurges, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, waues of diſcontent, and enmity; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, brittle as glaſſe: whiles riches take them the winges of an Eagle, and ſpeedily forſake
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:851:21"/>their owners: ſo to honour, beauty, ſtrength, the moſt glorious life therefore is but brittle, and troubleſome. Secondly, conſider a man plagued for his offences, with many croſſes, not one amongſt many, but taketh vp the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Iob,</hi> crying out, <hi>Wherefore is the light giuen to him that is in miſerie? and life vnto them that haue heauie hearts? which long for death, and if it come not, they would euen ſearch it more then treaſure? Iob.</hi> 3.20.21. But thirdly, conſider a good Chriſtian, who in his eſtate outwardly is content &amp; ſatisfied: he, no doubt, deſireth earneſtly to ſerue God ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet the beſt are diuerſe times ouertaken by ſinne, that they ſinne, and then repent, and by and by ſinne againe, and then repent againe, &amp; then ſinne againe, and repent againe: ſo that they are forced by ſinne creeping on ſo faſt, to cry out, <hi>O miſerable men that wee are, who ſhall deliuer vs from the body of this death, Rom.</hi> 7.24. Oh how bleſſed a thing is it to liue but ſuch a life, in ſuch a place, as not onely all teares ſhall be wiped from our eyes, but all ſinne from our ſoules, where wee ſhall bee fure, wee ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſinne more. In this life wee cannot but ſin. Thus meditating what this life is to all ſorts, thou wile bee helped to prepare thy ſelfe the more willingly to embrace death, and to <hi>put thy houſe, thy cloſet-houſe in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that wee may haue our ſoules the better prepared for death, let vs conſider the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:851:21"/>great change which ſhall happen to diuers men after death: many which haue ſeemed happy in this life, in the next life ſhall be moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, many which in this life haue ſeemed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, in the next worlde ſhould truely be moſt glorious: As appeareth by <hi>Lazarus,</hi> in this life moſt miſerable, in the next life moſt happy: as the <hi>Rich man</hi> after his coſtly raiment and delicious fare in this life, beggeth miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and is denyed vtterly a cuppe of water to coole his tongue. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did place <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> to the right hand of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and <hi>Ephraim</hi> to his left hand: but <hi>Iacob</hi> bleſſed <hi>Ephraim</hi> with his right hand, and <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> with his left, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. So many a one which in this life ſeemeth to bee at the right hand of God, by his many externall bleſſings, ſhall after death bee turned to the left hand of the vengeance of God: and contrarily, many that ſeeme now by their many calamities, to be at the left hand of the curſe of God, ſhall there be brought vnto the right hand of his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable glory. There are the priſoners at reſt, and heare not the voyce of the oppreſſor, There are the ſmall and the great, and the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant is free from his maiſter, <hi>Iob.</hi> 3.18.19. Some few ſhall be ſo happy, as both heere and there to bee at the right hand of God. Thinke now what thou art, thinke what change will follow and let this meditation helpe thee, to prepare thy ſelfe for death, to <hi>put thy houſe, thy cloſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:851:22"/>
               <p>And thus much for thoſe things, which help forward the cloſſet-houſe to be well ordered by meditation. Now to thoſe things which helpe it forward, and conſiſt in action. And thoſe I will reduce to foure heads, of which I will very briefly ſpeake.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that whoſoeuer will haue the houſe of his ſoule prepared againſt death, ſuffer in his ſoule no ſuch traitors or weapons as may helpe death againſt him, thoſe traytors, thoſe weapons are our ſinnes, <hi>The ſting of death is ſin,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56. as it appeareth in many a dying man and woman, dying with great impatience, not ſo much becauſe they muſt die, as that they are netled with the remembrance of ſuch and ſuch horrible ſins, for which as yet their peace is not made: then they curſe the time, not that they die in, but wherein they euer knew ſuch a man, or ſuch a woman, that hereby it eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth where the ſting of death lyeth: and is felt either before death, or after death: this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the diuell ſo buſie, now and then euery day to crowde one ſinne or other into our ſoules &amp; conſciences, as if he were now ſetting in a ſtaffe, now a dagger, now a ſword, now a gunne, now one weapon, now another, which hee might haue ready in our owne ſoules to wound our ſelues withall. If therefore wee will order our ſelues aright, let vs looke into the houſe of our ſoules, and ſee what weapons ſtand which may helpe the diuell and not vs, as all vnrepented
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:851:22"/>ſinnes doe, and let vs caſt them out: take out blaſphemy, curſing, oppreſſion, impatience, hypocriſie, fling them from you, that ſo you may <hi>put your houſe, your cloſet houſe in order,</hi> and thrice miſerable are they who giue the diuell leaue euery day, to crowd what weapons of ſin he liſt into their ſoules.</p>
               <p>Secondly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> in the houſe of the ſoule and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, there muſt be gotten a true and liuing faith, whereby not onely the weapons of the diuell muſt bee caſt out, but that Chriſt may enter, and dwell and keepe poſſeſſion in the ſoule, vntill it ſhall bee brought to glory. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which die in the Lord, Reuel.</hi> 14.13. <hi>All theſe dyed in the faith, Heb.</hi> 11 13. Dying <hi>Iacob</hi> out of faith could ſay, <hi>Lord I waite for thy ſaluation, Gen.</hi> 49. As hee that was ſtung by the fiery ſerpents, was to looke vnto the braſen ſerpent, and ſo recouer: ſo he that is ſtung by ſinne and death, muſt haue a liuing faith to beholde Ieſus Chriſt withall, and hee ſhall bee cured, <hi>Iohn.</hi> 3. Miſerable wordlings, when wealth and Phyſitians faile, their hope fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: A Chriſtian alwayes getteth faith, that thereby Chriſt may dwell with him here; that by Chriſt his ſinnes may bee couered, that by the touch (not of the hemme of Chriſt his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) but of Chriſt himſelfe, all the bloody iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues of his ſinnes may bee dryed vp: that when the eyes of his body grow dim by approaching death, hee may yet by the eyes of faith, ſee
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:851:23"/>Chriſt Iefus at the right hand of the Father, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for him, labour therefore that thou mayeſt bee faithfull, that ſo by faith, <hi>thy houſe, thy cloſet-houſe may be put in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the third action of the ſoule, to put it in order againſt death, is, that it bee alwayes willing to open the doore to God, to yeelde it ſelfe into the hands of God when God calleth. I know there was a time when <hi>Dauid</hi> prayed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death, ſaying, <hi>What profit is there in my blood, when I goe downe to the pit, Pſalm.</hi> 30.9. I know <hi>Ionah</hi> prayed earneſtly againſt it, <hi>Io.</hi> 3. and ſo did this good King <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> of whom wee ſpeake. There may be ſome ſecret cauſe, for the quieting of the conſcience after ſome great ſin, or recouering the glory of God, by the ſinne of his ſeruant impeached, or ſome ſuch like, <hi>Nolle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me hae in veſte, vt videat Thais,</hi> loth I am to die before my conſcience be fully ſetled, or I haue againe ſatisfied the Church of God after ſuch a ſin: or at ſuch a time as the Church hath moſt need of me, ſo as it cannot be well without me. Yet for all this, the Saints of God haue alwaies opened to God moſt willingly, when the time hath come that God would haue them: ſo olde <hi>Simeon, Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſeruant departe in peace according to thy word, Luk.</hi> 2.29. On the contrary, a wicked mans ſoule muſt be fetcht &amp; twitcht from him, <hi>This night ſhall they fetch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way thy ſoule from thee, Lu.</hi> 12. <hi>Malus eſt miles qui imperatore gemens ſequitur,</hi> He is a bad ſouldier
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:851:23"/>who followeth his Generall with ſighes &amp; ſobs. When one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; knocketh at your doores to ſpeake with you, if you perceiue him as hee is comming, and know him to be a friend you muſt vſe, you open the doores before hee can well knock; but if it bee one you deſire not to ſpeak with, then though you are within, yet will you anſwer not, &amp; beſides, your dores ſhall be faſt barred or locked. So when God commeth to ſome man and knocketh at his doore by ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; calleth, Thou ſoule of man come forth, and I muſt talke with you: away skuds the ſoul, barres the door with violent deſires to prolong life, with impatience at God his knocking, &amp; by no meanes will open, till God breaketh in vpon it: but when he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to another man full of grace, and knocketh at his body by ſicknes, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſuch a ſoule come forth, the Lord will ſpeake with thee: preſently anſwer is cheerfully made, <hi>Lord Ieſus receiue my ſpirit, Act.</hi> 7.59. <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larion</hi> (that holy Saint, as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> writeth) when hee was about to die, and felt in his ſoule an vnwillingneſſe to die, hee thus ſpake to his ſoule: <hi>Egredere anima, quid times? nonaginta tribus annis ſeruiuiſti Chriſto, &amp; mori times?</hi> Goe forth my ſoule, why feareſt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ninty &amp; three yeares haſt thou ſerued Chriſt, and art thou af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to die? Thus muſt the ſoule be prepared willingly to die, that ſo the <hi>cloſſet-houſe may bee put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> order againſt death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, as the bird flyeth to heauen-ward,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:851:24"/>not without wings, and the mariner paſſeth not the Sea without ſailes: ſo that the <hi>houſe of our ſoules may be put in order againſt death,</hi> muſt wee alwaies pray, that (if it may be, when God ſhall cloſe our mouthes, hee may cloſe them, not curſing, or altogether buſied about the worlde, but euen praying and calling vpon the name of the Lord. Thus the good conuerted theeſe dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth praying, <hi>Lord remember mee, when thou cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt into thy kingdome, Luke.</hi> 23.42. Thus out bleſſed Sauiour, <hi>Father into thy hands I commend my ſpirit, Luk.</hi> 23.46. Thus they ſtoned <hi>Steuen,</hi> who called vpon God, and ſayd, <hi>Lord Ieſus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue my ſpirit, Act.</hi> 7.59. Thus as <hi>Eliah</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into heauen with a fiery chariot: ſo much we, ſo muſt our ſoules aſcend in the middeſt of denout prayers; <hi>Thus moſt thou order thy cloſſet-houſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>Concluſion.</head>
               <p>Thus then haue wee ſeene the ſentence of death to haue beene irreuocable againſt vs all, and that we ought therefore to put our houſe in order, and how: now in a worde to conclude. When any of vs was in our mothers wombe, that ſhe began to look bigge with her burthen, there was made preparation for v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> before wee were borne, there were cloues prouided, a mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife and other wiues beſpoken, &amp; other things prepared againſt our birth into this world. The day of our death in this world, is but the day of our birth into another worlde. Wee come
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:851:24"/>out of the narrowe compaſſe of our mothers wombe, into this more ſpacious roome, fuller of brightneſſe: wee goe into another, which yeeldeth vs as many more pleaſing obiects the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the womb of this world yeeldeth, as this worlds womb yeeldeth more then our mothers womb. In the mothers wombe we ſomewhat (although but a little God wot) helpe our ſelues by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nouriſhment to our ſelues with our vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue faculty, before we come into this world, to the midwife and other wiues. Beholde, the ſpirit of God will be as the midwife, the bleſſed Angels will bee as the helping wiues, the bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of life eternal is inſteed of other clouts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided to wrape vp our ſoules in, in, in the time of our comming vnto the other world: onely now whiles we are in the wombe of the world, or rather of the Church of God, let vs by faith and charitie, our beleeuing and charitable powers, ſuck ſuch moiſture of grace, as that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes wee may ioyfully be receiued, <hi>as a childe borne into heauen, when wee ſhall haue put our houſes in order, for wee ſhall die, ane not liue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
